BBC Sounds, music, radio, podcasts.
Hello, I'm Brian Cox. I'm Robert Inks, and this is the Infinite Monkey Cage, and it is Christmas Day!
Happy Christmas!
Here's a shiny shilling, Brian Cox. Get me the finest turkey in the window.
Hope you got everything you wanted under the tree.
Brian didn't, unsurprisingly, because Brian got a particle accelerator, and he's got one of those already.
So I was like, I wanted a Hubble Space Telescope. No one understands me. I'm going back to my room to listen to Heaven 17.
Heaven 17?
Yeah, I thought Heaven 17 was quite a good choice for you. I thought you'd been into them.
It was either them or Flock of Seagulls, but Human League was kind of too mainstream, I thought.
So today, we're going to visit Father Christmas' home and see if we can find Santa and discover why Brian didn't get the presents that he demanded.
As usual, Robin is in a linear superposition of right and wrong, because we are going to the North Pole today, but not in search of Santa.
Though we will have a little look, won't we?
Maybe. But mainly, we'll be looking at how our proximity to the geomagnetic North Pole affects navigation.
What does the latest research tell us about the Northern Lights and the behaviour of our star?
And how is the polar environment changing, and what effect is that having on the flora and fauna of the far North?
And also, what is the best way of hosting a cocktail party at the North Pole?
Now, astonishingly, that last statement is part of the not wrong branch of Robin's wave function.
To help us explore, we are joined by an astrophysicist arctic explorer, a physiologist marine biologist, and a comedian with an antipathy to the aurora borealis, for some reason.
And they are...
My name is Felicity Aston. I'm a polar explorer.
And the coldest temperature I've ever experienced was not at the North Pole. I've been there several times.
It was actually in a place called the Pole of Cold, which is the coldest inhabited place in the world.
This is a tiny village called Omikon in the very northeast of Siberia.
And there's a population of about 300 people there, but their average wintertime temperature is below minus 70 degrees centigrade.
Oh my goodness.
Yeah.
Hi, I'm Lloyd Peck. I'm the physiologist marine biologist, and I'm a polar one.
I work for the British Antarctic Survey, and my thing is scuba diving underneath ice.
And the best way I've found in the past to keep warm when you're cold is to get in a sleeping bag with somebody else.
And body heat is a really good way of keeping warm.
Another story.
I'm Russell Kane. I'm a comedian. If you're over 50 and your name's Terry, you can put it in inverted commas.
And the coldest I've ever been was in Luton.
It was last December, just after Keir Starmer took my nan's radiator allowance away.
Well, that's ended a rather gloomy opening to us, hasn't it?
Now, I wish we'd done the Pole of Cold now. That seems upbeat, doesn't it?
Anyway, this is our panel.
Well, I suppose, really, to start off, Lucy, with you, one of the major questions a lot of people at home will be thinking about at the moment is
how difficult is it to build an enormous toy factory in an area like the North Pole?
I mean, what would be the issues?
I've been to the North Pole a number of times, and I go quite often into schools to talk about the Arctic and the North Pole and all these sorts of things.
And the question I always get asked, without fail, is have you ever seen Father Christmas or any elves at the North Pole?
And you can hear the collective intake of breath from all the adults in the room.
Like, you do not mess with Father Christmas.
And you can hear them thinking, what's she going to say? What's she going to say? What secrets is she going to give away?
But unfortunately, I have never seen any sign of Father Christmas or the elves at the North Pole, because it's magic, isn't it?
You're not supposed to see it.
But I have seen Father Christmas, but he's on the Arctic Circle in his office.
There is an office in Finland, just north of Rovaniemi, and Father Christmas is there pretty much every day with his elves.
And I have been to see him many times, not always accompanied by children.
So that is the place to go to see Father Christmas, not the North Pole.
So that is what I can reveal.
How do we define the North Pole? How is it defined?
Depends which North Pole you are talking about, because there are many North Poles on planet Earth.
The two that are absolute North Poles by anybody's definition is the Magnetic North Pole and the Geographic North Pole.
The Geographic North Pole is the one that everybody thinks of, the one at the top of our planet at 90 degrees north.
The Magnetic North Pole is the North Pole of our magnetic field that surrounds planet Earth.
So that's not too far away from the Geographic North Pole.
But then it starts to get a little bit more esoteric.
Some people think these are true North Poles, some people think it's a load of rubbish.
The Geomagnetic North Pole is like a theoretical North Pole.
This is if the Earth really was a definite bar magnet and we had a perfect magnetic field that was all nice and even and uniform,
then that's where our North Pole would be.
So this is the North Pole that's used by a lot of computer models.
But then you've got things like the Pole of Cold that I just mentioned.
And some people go, that's not really a proper North Pole.
And you've got the Pole of Inaccessibility, which is the place that is most inaccessible from all directions.
And you've got a Northern Pole of inaccessibility and a Southern Pole of inaccessibility.
And then you really do start to get a little bit bottom of the barrel.
So there's the Celestial North Pole.
That's not the bottom of the barrel!
Astronomers use this a lot because if you imagine that the sky is actually a sphere that surrounds the Earth,
then the North Pole of that celestial sphere, if you project that down onto the surface of the Earth,
then some people say, well, that's another North Pole on the surface of the planet.
So how many is that? Is that six? That's six.
So, you know, you could maybe stretch it to seven if you include the Pole of Cold.
So it's two kind of North Poles and then just some general flibbity-jibbity stuff.
You could go for three at least.
Do you reckon three?
I reckon you could go for three absolutely rock-solid ones.
Which are?
What's the third one then you go for?
So there's the Geographic, there's the Magnetic, and there's the Geomagnetic.
Oh, fair enough, yeah.
Those three you can measure. The others are subject to argument.
And so the Geomagnetic Pole is the one that's wandering.
The Geomagnetic Pole is fixed, it's the Magnetic one that's wandering.
So that one's wandering around.
And that one sometimes flips.
So hang on, right, look, this is going to be an absolute.
I'll tell you what, considering most of the people listening at home are drunk already on Christmas Day,
this is not following Christian values.
So where is the Magnetic North Pole now?
Well, for ages it was sort of floating around the Queen Elizabeth Islands in northern Canada,
Northwest Territories and Nunavut.
But then the last ten years it started really accelerating,
so it started moving 50 to 70 kilometres in a year.
So it's gone right the way across the Arctic Ocean,
it's now closer to the coast of Siberia than it is to the coast of Canada.
It'll never go south though, will it?
Like it won't go on tour and appear in Manchester or something.
It will.
Yeah, it will.
But it'll come here.
Well, it'll go down to the South Pole.
But it doesn't actually, it doesn't keep, let's just get this clear,
it doesn't kind of keep sliding down, does it?
There's a point, isn't there, when it flips.
So it doesn't kind of just go, oh, it's just gone past Guernsey.
I'm not sure.
It doesn't do that, does it?
No, it's a bit like the expansion of the Big Bang.
You know, there's definite theories,
but no one yet knows which of those theories are right.
So one theory is that our magnetic field will slowly decrease until there's nothing,
and then it will reappear equally gradually over time in a different orientation.
Another theory is that it's an instant flip
and that we might get lots of flips really rapidly.
But, I mean, we're talking rapidly over geological time.
We have a record of it, don't we?
Because we have essentially a barcode across the Atlantic, for example,
when rocks cool and they line up with the magnetic field.
So we can see when it flips in the past.
And it's quite, it's irregular, isn't it?
We should say this is the North Pole to which your compass points.
And then the question arises, as an explorer, is that a problem?
Yeah.
Your compass is pointing to different places.
Yeah, okay.
So the last time I skied to the North Pole,
a helicopter set me down on the frozen surface of the Arctic Ocean
about 80 kilometres away from the North Pole.
And I have to find my way to the North Pole.
There's nothing to see out there.
So every direction looks exactly the same.
So what do you do?
Do you use a compass?
But the problem with a compass is that it's pointing not to the geographic North Pole
that you're aiming towards.
It's pointing towards the magnetic North Pole,
which is several hundred kilometres away from the geographic North Pole.
And occasionally in Canada and occasionally in Siberia.
Exactly.
So you can't really use a compass.
And the other difficulty is that the difference between the magnetic North Pole
and the geographic North Pole changes depending on your location.
It's called declination.
So you have to know what the declination is
so that you can use a compass to direct you to the geographic North Pole.
And you're trying to do that while the ice that you're standing on is also moving
in an erratic motion, not always at the same speed or in the same direction.
So then you think, well, I'll use a GPS then.
So, yeah, okay, you can use a GPS.
But you're at temperatures of maybe minus 40 degrees centigrade.
And every handheld GPS device that there is uses batteries of some description.
And they run down very quickly at those sorts of temperatures.
So you can't always navigate using a GPS.
So unless you're going to drag out a sextant, which, you know,
they used to use in the old days.
But that's working out your position based on the position of the sun.
A bit difficult when it's really cloudy and you can't see the sun.
So all of these different methods of finding your way to the North Pole
have their inherent disadvantages in them.
And so you end up sort of using a bit of a mishmash of all of it.
So you go, oh, we'll just go to the right a little bit.
And then maybe the ice will drift us back on to the North Pole and all will be good.
So it's all a bit of a guessing game.
I can't get anywhere without a sat-nav.
I'll just be dead within.
How did you get there?
I mean, it explains why I've never seen Father Christmas, doesn't it?
I mean, maybe I've never actually been to the North Pole
and it's all just been a big mistake.
Lloyd, you make it even more difficult for yourself by diving under it.
Could you actually outline what the challenges are
in diving in the Arctic Ocean and in Antarctica?
So in one sense, we don't have it more difficult
because we usually know where we are.
And we've got batteries in our GPS system,
so we're pretty good because we're not out for days and weeks on our own.
So our location is pretty good.
The way we dive through ice is we take out a five-foot chain saw
and we cut oxo patterns in the ice until we get a block.
And the problem with that is that as you cut lines with your five-foot chainsaw,
it freezes behind the chainsaw.
So it probably takes you about three hours to dig a hole in the ice.
And you're looking aghast.
Yeah, good one for the council.
The pothole rate is about the same.
And then you bounce the blocks in the middle out
and you pull them out with a skidoo
and you're left with a hole that's about...
And you think, I'm going to dive in that.
Well, yeah.
Not only that, you think, I'm going to dive in that because that's great.
That's the best diving you are ever going to do on the planet anyway.
What is it about that diving?
So there are several things.
One is that that time of year when the sea is frozen,
everything settles out of the ocean
and the visibility is hundreds of metres.
Wow.
And you can see all this life that's around you on the seabed
that you wouldn't otherwise be able to see
because in the summertime when the phytoplankton blooms are on,
you can't see your hand at the end of your arm,
so you don't see anything.
But you said the hole freezes over.
So the hole does freeze over.
So if we want to go back to the same place day after day after day,
we put a cover over it.
What's the cover made of then?
Everything else bloody freezes.
Well, we use plywood.
LAUGHTER
Was anyone else expecting something more scientific?
Because plywood's easy to get out and easy to retrieve
and it's flexible enough.
It doesn't break like plastic does when it's cold.
You said that you see the life in the winter
when the visibility's good.
Can you describe the kinds of life you see
and the differences between the North and South Poles?
One of the great things that gets me excited
about life in the polar regions
is that some of it gets really big.
So, and I did bring a couple of examples...
Yes!
..that I have in my box.
We all know wood lice, yeah?
That's a group of animals called isopods.
Well, in the oceans, there are lots of isopods
and they get bigger as it gets colder.
And this is one that you would find in the Arctic.
It looks like something from Star Wars that would kill you.
You should edit this so it's the end of the show
and everyone goes, and this we found,
everyone went, ooh, and then it just stops.
LAUGHTER
And that's the end. A scream.
It's alive!
It's gone into my mouth!
LAUGHTER
So is that...
If a lobster and a wood louse had too much Sambuca
to put it on, that would be their kid.
So they get up to 10cm, four inches long.
They are hundreds of times bigger
than the biggest isopods that we have around our coasts.
And Felicity, earlier, didn't you say that they jumped at you?
Yeah, so when I was stationed at Rothera Research Station,
which is a British Antarctic Survey research base
on the Antarctic Peninsula,
there was a marine biology building
that had these big aquariums.
And part of the wintering job that you had to do
was that you had to do night watch.
One of the jobs that we had to do was sent to us by Lloyd.
He was like, you need to check my aquariums
to make sure that, you know, all the little beasties
that we've collected are all doing all right.
So middle of the night, I've been on my own all night in the dark
in an Antarctic research station
looking like a 70s horror movie set.
And so I let myself into this dark aquarium lab
and it's all dark, but apart from the red floodlights.
So it looks like that scene from Alien, right?
Where there's something scuttling underneath all the lab desks.
And I noticed that one of the covers
that were over the top of the aquarium
had been left partly off.
And the reason those covers were on the aquarium
is because those little woodlouse creatures
like to jump out of the tanks to anyone that's passing by.
And if they land on you, they stick to you.
You can't get them off very easily.
So I was seeing that, I was like, oh no,
I've got to go and put that cover back on the aquarium
and these things are going to jump out at me in the dark
in this red light.
But I managed to get them on
and I didn't get attacked by a woodlouse.
I've got a question.
Does Imodium freeze?
Because I would need a lot of it to survive that scenario.
Oh no, you wouldn't.
Honestly, it would be...
Who was that guy, do you remember,
when we went to the Adventurers Club?
The Explorers Club.
The Explorers Club, that was it.
And he, when he got trapped underground,
realised that because sometimes dog excrement,
you could actually turn into a pic
because it would freeze hard.
So he did a big poo and then chipped his way out
with his own excrement.
And he also lost a leg and ate some of his own leg.
I'll stick with Imodium, it sounds more convenient.
So to come back to the large animals,
the real big story here is not the isopods.
It's these guys.
So, listeners, it looks...
It's like a star-shaped, spider-esque,
daddy-long-leg thing,
but it's the size of two adult hands.
Very thin legs.
It's a massive spider.
Sorry to be pedantic, but how many legs does it have?
It looks more like a living asterisk,
so you can all count, can't you?
It's got ten legs.
So, taxonomically, is it a spider?
No, taxonomically...
Indeed, indeed, Poirot.
However, there's a big story to this as well.
95% of sea spiders in the world have eight legs.
But in the Antarctic, you get ten-legged species
and 12-legged species.
And the biggest ones are three times as big as this.
They're 60 to 70 centimetres across,
and they are 5,000 times bigger than the biggest sea spiders
that we get in temperate latitudes.
Not poisonous, not bitey?
Well, they move very slowly,
and if you were to put your hand underneath its mouth
and hold it there for three or four hours,
you might get bitten.
You've done that, haven't you?
Week five of the expedition, I'm going to do it.
So, why...
Because many people have heard of island gigantism.
What is it about the ocean, the Arctic oceans,
that leads to this size?
So, the polar oceans are different in many ways
from the oceans elsewhere in the world.
If you go into the high polar oceans,
the sea temperature is permanently below zero degrees.
And that has extra characteristics.
One is, the amount of oxygen you can squeeze into water
increases as you cool it down.
And that's, in simple terms,
it's because the molecules in the water move more slowly,
the gaps get bigger, and you can force more in between the gaps.
And there's nearly twice as much oxygen in seawater
at the polar regions as the tropics.
So, one, more oxygen to feed the tissues.
Two, these are all cold-blooded animals,
and that means their body temperatures are the same as the environment.
And, because their body temperatures are below zero,
their respiration rates, their amount of energy they need
to keep their bodies going,
is 25 to 30 times less than at the tropics.
So, there's more oxygen, twice as much.
25 times slower rate of use.
Two times 25 is 50.
You have a massive increased path length for supplying your tissues,
which means you can grow more tissues.
You mentioned just that the body temperature is the same temperature as the ocean,
as the water, and you said below freezing.
Yeah.
So, why doesn't it freeze?
So, this is one of my lectures to undergraduates that takes about an hour.
So, if you're all sitting comfortably.
Well done, Brian.
So, if you look at living cells,
they have to stay liquid.
And, there are various ways that you can keep that cytoplasm,
that cellular content liquid.
One is you can use antifreezes.
And, fish in the polar regions produce protein antifreezes and glycoprotein antifreezes.
So, they make proteins that basically, when an ice crystal starts to form,
they stick to the front of the ice crystal like cling film
and stop more water coming on.
Then, they can use a whole range of things,
things like glycerol and things like glucose,
to change the point at which that liquid would freeze.
In the same way that we can put salt into water and lower the freezing point.
Vodka in the freezer.
Yeah, yeah.
So, if you drink a lot of vodka,
you'd have to go to a lower temperature before you froze,
which I guess a lot of people in Newcastle on a Saturday night do, isn't it?
So, you can do all of that.
But, then they can also control the amount of water in their cells.
And, when it comes to wintertime in the Arctic,
the different ways that animals survive the cold is absolutely mind-boggling.
If you go and look in Canada at the red bark beetle, it has larvae.
That starts off using glycerol and it goes down to about minus 20 with glycerol.
Then, it pumps the water out of its cells,
so there's less chance of water molecules sticking together.
It gets down below minus 40.
And then, when it gets down below minus 40 towards minus 50,
it vitrifies.
And, the problem with freezing is the ice crystals break your cells open and kill you.
But, if you vitrify, you turn into glass and there are no ice crystals.
And, those bark beetle larvae have been taken down to minus 150.
Wow.
And, survive.
Can I ask a question?
Is it ageing still at this point or is it in stasis?
So, if it was to stay frozen and it was to defrost 300 years later,
would it be the same age as when it froze?
That's a really, really, really good area of research.
It is in stasis.
And, is it possible we could ever use this technology to stop human ageing
so we could travel to distant stars and things like that?
So, cryogenesis, yes, that is possible.
In the 1950s, there was a lot of work done on freezing mammals.
And, they were able to freeze mice and they couldn't do it with rabbits.
And, the problem is not with freezing them.
The problem is warming them up.
Because, if everything does not warm up at the same rate
and something goes liquid while something else is solid,
your animal is not going to function.
And, that was the research that led to the invention of microwave ovens.
Wow.
So, they microwave them to warm them up?
I could have told them that wasn't going to work.
Where's Nan?
She's on defrost.
She'll be 10 minutes.
This has changed a lot of people's Christmas lunch.
Absolutely fascinating.
We've spoken about the life that we see underwater.
So, in terms of the life that you've seen on your expeditions,
what's the variety of animals that you see on the surface?
Yeah.
I mean, this is the wonderful thing about going to the North Pole
versus going to the South Pole.
And, one of the defining characteristics of the Antarctic Plateau
in the center of Antarctica is the absence of life.
I mean, there's no wildlife there.
There's no penguins or seals or birds or anything like that.
But, when you are up in the North, you are surrounded by life,
even if you're right up there in the middle of the Arctic Ocean.
And, it's not just that you see it, it's that you can feel it all around you
from the presence of the big predators, the polar bears,
right down to when a big chunk of ice turns over
and there's lots of algae and even fish using the algae.
I remember being startled by a lemming in my tent when I was about...
That'd make you fall off a cliff, didn't it?
That'd be the most ironic day in history.
And, you're thinking, how does this tiny little thing, you know,
manage to survive all the way out here?
It's really incredible.
Everyone has a polar bear story.
Surely, every explorer has a polar bear story.
I'm glad you narrowed that down.
Everyone has... No, actually, I shouldn't...
I just wondered, in terms of jeopardy,
you talked about big predators.
So, what's your big predator story?
Oh, gosh.
The closest encounter I've had with a polar bear,
luckily, I was on a snow machine.
So, I was driving by myself on a snow machine
past a big area of ice...
So, that's a machine that goes on snow, not a machine that makes snow.
Exactly. A snowmobile, a skidoo, whatever you want to call it.
And I was keeping an eye on the ice rubble
because that's where the polar bears kind of like to hang out.
And I came over a rise to find one
sort of stood pretty much right in front of me.
I was close enough to really see the sort of definition of its muscles.
I mean, these are frightening animals.
And the number of people that said,
oh, I really want to see a polar bear.
It's like, you really don't.
And so, luckily, I was on a snowmobile
and I knew that I was in an area
where the locals hunted them on snow machines.
So, I was able just to rev the engine a bit
and it got up on its back legs, took a big sniff.
And, you know, my heart was sort of in my mouth as it's doing this
and then it just took off and ran.
So, I didn't have to even get the rifle off my back.
It was a bit warm after that encounter, wasn't it?
If you go and work in Svalbard
and you go to the UK station in Svalbard,
the first thing they do on the first day is
they give you a .375 rifle.
And that has bullets that are bigger than anything you've seen in a rifle before.
They train you how to shoot it
and they give you thunder flashes
so that if the polar bear starts coming towards you,
you're supposed to throw the thunder flashes between you and the polar bear
and the bangs make it go away.
And then they say, if that doesn't happen,
then you have a rifle if you can't get away from it in time.
And, if it worse comes to worse,
you have to shoot the polar bear.
Now, you're on Norwegian territory
and the law says you are not allowed to shoot a polar bear
unless it is less than 10 metres away from you.
And a full-sized polar bear does 11 metres per second.
And then they say, the last time one of these was killed,
it took three bullets to kill it.
So, the best advice is, if it starts stalking you,
get out of the way really quickly.
Yeah, so if you come across a bear when you're on an expedition,
the only responsible thing to do is to get yourself out of there
because we are intruders in their territory.
We are intruders in their territory.
My life is less valuable than the bears in that scenario,
is what you're telling me.
Yes.
They are nine feet tall
and they are heavier than any two people that you know.
So, they are massive animals.
Now, we're going to do...
Because you, I believe this is true,
you have in the Guinness Book of World Records
for the most polar bears shot...
Oh, God, no, we haven't hit that yet.
You are in the Guinness Book of Records
for the northernmost cocktail party.
Yes, that is a Guinness World Record that I currently hold.
So, I was on an expedition
and we were right up at 78 degrees north.
So, as you imagine, like polar explorers are in a tent
and all the polar gear with skis and everything else.
But in order for it to be considered a cocktail party
by the Guinness Book of Records,
there's a very specific set of criteria that you have to follow.
So, there has to be at least five people.
Tick, we were a five-person team.
You have to be in proper cocktail attire.
So, that is a dress for women.
I mean, you know, the Guinness World Records
have got something to answer about sort of...
And if you're a man, it's a proper lounge suit
or a lounge dress, cocktail dress.
You have to have music playing.
You have to have a table with a tablecloth.
I'm already thinking most of the parties I've ever been to in my life
are already not considered a cocktail party by this.
You have to have at least three different types of cocktails
and you have to have two different types of canapé,
one sweet and one savoury.
Oh, and it has to last for at least 15 minutes.
We had to sort of drink it quickly
before it froze into a sort of icicle in the bottom of the glass.
God, it goes straight to your head.
How did you defrost the canapés?
Oh, I knew you were going to ask that.
So the cocktails were ready-mixed
and we took them in, like, these little packages.
We had to defrost those by sort of putting them down our fronts.
I knew it.
The warmest part.
So, you know, under your armpit is one of the warmest pits
and down your pants, whatever.
But they were all enclosed, so that was fine.
But the canapés, yeah, our canapés,
we had to get inventive using the rations that we had.
We are going to now try and create aurora-based cocktails
using a UV light.
So what we've got in these glasses here is a gin and tonic.
Just to say, because I arrived quite late for this recording,
I have no idea what's going on.
Oh, neither do I.
Is there some context about why you've got a UV light and some gin?
Do you know what, Brian, you've never complained before
when we found reasons that we can have alcohol in
which appear to be tax-deductible.
No, I have a vague memory of something now
in some production meeting a while ago.
So this is...
Something about the northern lights.
So that there, using a small amount of blue liqueur-style drink
and a Barocca and a UV light,
all of those things you probably receive for Christmas.
So just to recap, so this is an elaborate introduction
to the aurora borealis.
Yeah, what is happening in the atmosphere that creates that kind of,
that's the greenness of the aurora borealis?
Yeah, so if we rewind a bit to what the aurora is,
so if you imagine the Earth is a big bar magnet
and we have this big magnetic field that spreads all the way around the globe
and that creates this sort of area of space around the planet
called the magnetosphere,
and then you have the sun in the middle of the solar system
that is constantly sort of emitting this wind of charged particles.
So it's this huge amount of charged particles
that are cascading from the sun outwards across the whole solar system.
And instead of hitting the Earth, it hits the magnetosphere.
And because these particles are charged,
they react with that magnetic field that surrounds the planet.
So it acts as a sort of shield.
It protects us from the solar wind, from all this radiation.
But some of those charged particles
sort of get trapped inside the magnetic field of the Earth.
And if you can imagine sort of around the poles,
let's focus on the North Pole,
around the North Pole where the magnetic field lines
are sort of going into the top of the planet,
all these charged particles that are spinning around
all these magnetic field lines
are being dragged down towards the surface of the planet
around the North Pole.
And where those charged particles
start getting dragged through the atmosphere,
they start interacting with other particles that are in the atmosphere,
so things like oxygen and nitrogen predominantly.
And so when a charged particle starts interacting with some oxygen,
it will start getting really excited and emitting light as photons.
And we see that light as green if it's interacting with oxygen,
but we'll see it as different colours
depending on which gas it's interacting with.
And there's so much a part of the Arctic,
of the experience, the aurora, both north and south.
So they become part of the mythology in the Northern Lights,
part of the cultures of the Arctic.
Hugely.
The first time I saw the Northern Lights,
I knew about the science.
I knew how they were caused according to European science.
You know, we have the explanation.
And yet sitting there watching this phenomenon for the first time,
that seemed like the least likely explanation.
Magic seemed like a lot more realistic explanation of what I was seeing.
I think it's important to say that this is a lot of people's beliefs,
and I in no way am sort of sneering or laughing at that
because the first time I saw it, that was what I saw.
I saw spirits moving across a bridge to another world.
And it's reflected in a lot of different cultures.
So one of the loveliest stories I heard
was actually from First Nation tribes north of the Great Plains.
And they had a folkloric hero, a mythical hero,
almost like a god-like figure,
who, once he'd finished creating the world,
they believed travelled north.
And so that he could send a message back to his people
that he hadn't forgotten them,
he would light a massive fire.
And this is what the Northern Lights was.
It was a reflection of this massive fire.
And whenever I see the Northern Lights now,
that story springs into mind
because it really does feel like you're seeing something
that connects you, not only to people around the world,
but also connects you to the solar system and everything beyond that.
This is created by something that's come from the sun.
It's really incredible.
Is it a very, very different experience being in the northern Arctic,
where you have all these rich cultural stories,
and then the Antarctic,
where there's essentially nobody other than scientists?
Well, it is massively different
because the north is an ocean,
and the south is a massive continent,
a continent twice the size of Australia.
And it contains...
It's rock underneath it, yeah.
And there's no rock at the surface in the north.
It's an ocean.
And the Antarctic contains about three-quarters of the world's fresh water.
So the amount of ice in the Antarctic is absolutely unreal.
It's an area the size of Europe that's two miles thick.
I'd like to ask about the impact of climate change
on these areas in the Arctic and the Antarctic.
So what are we seeing change
over the years and decades that you've visited those areas?
So the biggest change, I think, is the loss of ice.
So in the Arctic in the 1970s,
we had 15,000 square kilometres of sea ice,
and now we've got five.
And the predictions are that by 2050, in the summer,
that minimum extent...
and that's the minimum extent of ice in the Arctic...
will have gone, and it'll be open water in the Arctic,
so people will be able to sail ships through the Arctic.
You mentioned earlier the ice turns over,
and it's green, and it's thick green.
And huge numbers of species live on the underside of that ice,
including the early life stages of things like polar cod.
And lots of organisms depend on that ice for their life cycles.
So the effect on the ecosystem is massive.
And all the timings change,
and the ability of animals to raise themselves efficiently,
or even at all, becomes a really difficult problem.
And we know there are tipping points in the environment.
We know there are tipping points not just in the environment,
but in ecosystems.
And in the polar regions,
we don't know how much we can lose from an ecosystem
before it collapses.
Felicity, how does that change in terms of your experience now,
and knowing this fragility, how different is it for you?
Really emotionally, I suppose.
It's really odd, because if you're in the middle of the Arctic Ocean,
you know how fragile this environment is.
And yet, when you're there, seeing big blocks of ice
coming up one over the other,
and size of apartment blocks being just tossed over,
it feels anything but fragile when you're in that moment.
But it's not just the amount of ice being so much less.
It's the fact that what is there now is thinner, newer,
and less stable than it's ever been before.
Whereas, say, in 1969,
when Sir Wally Herbert crossed the Arctic Ocean
and became the first team of people
to undisputedly get to the top of our planet,
get to the North Pole.
But that journey is no longer possible,
because they did it when there was lots of what we call multi-year ice.
So this is the thick stuff.
It can be three metres or more,
and it's really stable, really strong,
and it holds the pack ice together.
The last time a polar explorer went from land to the North Pole
across the Arctic Ocean was in 2014.
It's not been possible to do it since then.
So now it's only possible to do partial journeys to the North Pole.
Russell, what are your final thoughts on everything you've heard today?
I always get invited on this programme,
and I never know anything about the subject.
I'm sort of like a student.
But I have actually seen the Northern Lights,
and I have actually been to the Arctic Circle
for a project I was filming.
It was a sort of comedy survival programme.
So I've seen this majestic spectacle,
and I was invited by the Sami,
the people in the northern part of Norway,
and I went into something called a lavu,
which is their conical-shaped traditional hut.
I was invited for dinner,
and in this programme I had two YouTubers with me called Rose and Rosie,
and they'd been stressing all trip because they were vegetarians.
I don't think a word even exists in their language.
We had to try to explain to these people what vegetarian was.
And when we got there, obviously I eat anything
because I'm a moron from a council estate,
and when I got there, dinner was...
You couldn't have done a more comically shocking snack for vegans.
It was a boiled reindeer's head,
which was out, and everyone was happily picking the bits of meat off.
I mean, it just tasted like meat.
It just looked... Obviously the eye holes and everything.
And these girls were starting to cry and panicking.
The producer's like, OK...
And the translator said,
don't worry, he's got something without meat for you two.
And it was a pancake made from blood.
LAUGHTER
It was delicious!
But, yeah, I've been there. It's like another planet.
It's hard to explain if you haven't done it.
The more that we express the fascination, the beauty, the curiosity
and how much you can fall in love with the possibilities that are there,
then the more I think we strive to try and preserve what is there as well.
Experiencing what the world has out there
is just way more intense than anything that you can get within a city.
And I would say the Northern Lights, the Southern Lights,
that's one of a whole plethora of things and experiences
that most people don't get.
But if you have experienced them,
they become a substantial part of the way you function and the way you live.
And it has effects that go beyond what you can get
by understanding what it is.
Well, we also asked our audience...
By the way, I'll just tell you, you know the guy I told you about
who had one leg who did a poo and then used it as a pickaxe?
Peter Freuchen.
Anyway, so we always ask the audience a question
because we have the most intelligent audience of any Radio 4 show.
And I don't care what you say, Gardner's Question Time,
I'll meet you out the back of the allotments and take you on.
Is that a poo knife?
Call that a poo knife?
This is a poo knife.
This is a very strange remake of Crocodile Dundee.
That's not a poo. This is a poo.
So we asked our audience,
if you were going to make a snowman resembling anyone,
who would it be and why?
Is that the first one you got?
Hugh Jackman, I think this should be, shouldn't it?
Do you know why?
Hugh Jackman.
What films has he been in?
Wolverine.
By the way, if you ever want to be a Wolverine at home,
just put Potato Grater Snowman on the...
The Greatest Snowman.
Brian Cox building a snowman of himself
because things can only get meta.
Well done, well done.
I think I beat that, I beat that.
Oh, come on then.
It's not Brian Cox-based.
I know you like them to be based on YouTube, but this isn't.
If you could build a really big one with a six-pack,
it would be the Abdominal Snowman.
Oh, very nice, yeah.
Okay then, well, thank you very much to our wonderful panel.
Felicity Aston, Lloyd Peck and Russell Kane.
Next week it's, well, it's 2026
and we're going to be taking a bit of a break
so Brian can tour the world
and I can watch every episode of The Professionals
on daytime TV
because I've always seen myself as a bit of a Martin Shorty
or Lewis Collins.
I think you're more Cowley, don't you?
A woolly jumper and a...
He doesn't have a woolly jumper, he's got a tweedy jacket.
A tweedy jacket and a scotch and a jag.
That's what I see you as.
That's Arthur Daly, isn't it?
Anyway, as we're having a bit of a break,
this week's homework is a 500-word essay
on how Archimedes' principles
affect the flotation of Brian's ivory bath ducks
or, for the more adventurous amongst you,
using balsa wood, paper straws, three-glass marbles
and one item of your own choosing,
make a perpetual motion machine
and send it to BBC TV centre Wood Lane.
I'm sorry, but we're unable to return
your perpetual motion machines.
If you return them back again and so on and so on and so on.
Bye!
Bye-bye!
APPLAUSE
MUSIC PLAYS
Turn that nice again.
Political language can seem archaic.
It's like the light from one of those stars that actually died.
Sometimes bamboozling.
It's a theme park with a five-foot log flume
from one thought to another.
And very often beyond words.
I don't know how to describe the language that you use.
I'm Armando Iannucci.
I'm all reset and turbocharged to stress-tested destruction,
used and abused buzzwords and phrases
from the world of politics.
I come with a dazzling array of guest presenters
and I'll be exploring the verbal tricks of the political trade,
the intentions behind them and the effect they have on all of us.
The new series of Strong Message here with me, Armando Iannucci,
from BBC Radio 4.
Listen now on BBC Science.